<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Minä Blog</title>
        <link>https://xh313.github.io/mina/blog</link>
        <description>Minä Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[French Take 2...]]></title>
            <link>https://xh313.github.io/mina/blog/french-take-two</link>
            <guid>french-take-two</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[J'ai finalement changé la langue de mon téléphone du finnois au français après un an... // I finally changed my phone language from Finnish to French after a year...]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>J&#x27;ai finalement changé la langue de mon téléphone du finnois au français après un an... // I finally changed my phone language from Finnish to French after a year...</p><h2>En Français</h2><p>J&#x27;ai finalement changé la langue de mon téléphone du finnois au français après un an. J&#x27;espère que je n&#x27;oublierai pas le finnois, mais je dois vraiment commencer à rafraîchir mon français si je ne veux pas échouer à mon cours de français le semestre prochain 🥲</p><p>Si vous souhaitez savoir comment se déroule mon apprentissage du français et en quoi il est différent de celui du finnois, consultez mon blogue linguistique !</p><h2>In English (DeepL translated)</h2><p>I finally changed my phone language from Finnish to French after a year. I hope I won&#x27;t forget Finnish, but I really need to start brushing up on my French if I don&#x27;t want to fail my French class next semester 🥲</p><p>If you want to know how my French learning is going and how it is different from Finnish, check out my language blog!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Diary in Rovaniemi 🙄]]></title>
            <link>https://xh313.github.io/mina/blog/paivakirja-rovaniemella</link>
            <guid>paivakirja-rovaniemella</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Päiväkirja Rovaniemella 🙄]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Päiväkirja Rovaniemella 🙄</p><h2>Suomeksi</h2><p>Rovaniemen Ruokasenkadulla ei ole ollenkaan ruokaa (vaan hautauspalvelua, tietenkin), ja kaaduin kadulla jäässä 5 kertaa päivässä.
<img src="./hautauspalvelut.jpg" alt="Hautauspalvelut"/></p><blockquote><p>Hautauspalvelut Ruokasenkadulla.</p></blockquote><p>Mutta mielestäni mukaan, Rovaniemi oli muutakin kuin tylsyyttä. Ainakin ei kukaan enää vastannut englanniksi kun aloitin vuoropuheluja suomeksi. Sen takia olen oppinut yhtä paljon suomea kuin olen kaatunut lumessa. Mutta, kaikki puhuikin suomea kaverini kanssa, ja he eivät pystynyt ymmärtämään mitään kuitenkin.</p><p>Joulupukkia tai revontulia ei ollenkaan näy. Vain käyn taidemuseossa katsomassa, koska yksi kadulla olevien matkustajista suositteli. Mutta mieleni harhaili kuin kuvassa (tulossa löytyy).</p><p>Sitten menimme mäkeen, jolla oli paljon lunta. Allen teki lumiukon, ja sitten vahvasti potkii sen päähän. En tiedä mitä saan ajatella tästä.</p><p><img src="./lumiukko.jpg" alt="Potkaistu lumiukko"/></p><blockquote><p>Allen potkaisi lumiukon.</p></blockquote><p>En tiedä miksi maksoin melkein puoli budjetistani käydä tässä. Se sai minut kysymään itseltä elämästäni. Nyt odotan lennon takaisin Helsinkiin, ja ajattelen, että eilen Rovaniemellä vain oli totaalista outoa unta. No, ehkä on myös elämystä. En ole varma.</p><h2>In English</h2><p><strong>Diary in Rovaniemi. 🙄</strong></p><p>There is no food at all on Ruokasenkatu (‘Foody street’ if I literally interpret it) in Rovaniemi (but only a funeral service, of course), and I fell on icy streets 5 times a day.</p><p>But I think Rovaniemi wasn’t quite just boring. At least nobody answered in English anymore when I started dialogues in Finnish. As a result, I have learned as much Finnish as I have fallen in the snow. But everyone spoke Finnish with my friends too, and they couldn&#x27;t understand anything anyway.
There was no Santa Claus or northern lights at all. I only went to check out the art museum because one of the random passengers on the street recommended it. But my mind wandered as in the picture.</p><p><img src="./harhailla.jpg" alt="Mieleni harhaili"/></p><blockquote><p>Mieleni harhaili taidemuseossa.</p></blockquote><p>Then we went to a hill with a lot of snow on it. Allen made a snowman, and then brutally kicked it in the head. I don&#x27;t know what to make of this.
<img src="./lumiukko.jpg" alt="Potkaistu lumiukko"/></p><blockquote><p>Allen kicking the snowman.</p></blockquote><p>I don&#x27;t know why I spent almost half my budget to visit this place. It made me question myself about my life. Now waiting for my flight back to Helsinki, I&#x27;m thinking that yesterday in Rovaniemi was just an absolutely weird dream. Well, maybe there is an experience too. I&#x27;m not sure.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 5th month studying Finnish]]></title>
            <link>https://xh313.github.io/mina/blog/viides-kuukausi</link>
            <guid>viides-kuukausi</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Suomeksi]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Suomeksi</h2><p>Tänään on sattumalta viides kuukausi siitä, kun aloitin suomea opiskelun, mutta en edes ehdi juhlimiselle pieni hetki. Se on liian traaginen ja en pysty keskustelemaan enää sitä.</p><p>Olen palanut itseasiassa melkein loppuun itseni nykyisin ja en jaksa mitään. Kirjoitin vähän, koska se on ehkä erityinen päivä, vaikka olenhan vielä niin epäonnistunut tässä kielessä ja minulla en ole vapaa oppimiselle kuitenkin. Puhun sitä yhtä huonosti kuin paska, eli lopetan tähän.</p><h2>In English</h2><p>Today happens to be the fifth month since I started studying Finnish, but I don&#x27;t even have a small moment to celebrate. It&#x27;s too tragic and I can&#x27;t discuss it anymore. I&#x27;m actually almost burnt out on myself these days and I can&#x27;t take anything. I wrote a bit because it is perhaps a special day, although I am still so unsuccessful in this language and I don’t have free time for learning it anyway. I speak it as bad as shit, so I&#x27;ll stop here.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Chinese or Japanese harder to learn for Finnish speakers?]]></title>
            <link>https://xh313.github.io/mina/blog/quora-ans-cn-jp</link>
            <guid>quora-ans-cn-jp</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Original post link here.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Original post link <a href="https://qr.ae/pvHn6B">here</a>.</p><h2>Suomeksi</h2><p>Äidinkieleni on kiina (mandarin) ja osaankin vähän japania (opettelin sitä noin 2 vuotta lapsuudessa mutta puhun vielä huonosti). Minun on vaikea vastata sinun kysymykseen, koska maailmassa ei ole varmasti helpompi kieltä kaikille. Se on tosi subjektiivinen aihe ja perustuu vahvasti siihen, että mikä äidinkielesi on, ja sitten mitkä muita kieliä sinä voit puhua.</p><p>UNESCO julkaisi sijoitusta, jossa kirjoitetaan että japanin kieli on vaikeampi kuin kiinan englanninkieliselle (linkki on täällä: Language Difficulty Ranking - Effective Language Learning).</p><p>Mutta mielestäni tää ei ole välttämättä totta suomenkieliselle, koska kuin opettelen suomea nykyisin, tajuan usein että japanin kieli on niin samanlainen kuin suomi. Ensinnä, sanaa lausutaan samanlaisella tavalla suomeksi ja japaniksi, joissa on pitkiä vokaaleja ja konsonantteja (esim. tuuli≠tuli, ちょっと≠ちょと). Kiinan kielellä ei ole sitä, mut on kuitenkin 4 toonia (esim. 也yě≠叶yè≠爷yé). Siksi tarvitset tehdä erityistä ’säveltä’ joka tavu kiinaksi, ja jos et vielä puhu tonaalisia kieliä, saatat ajatella että se on erittäin vaikea…</p><p>Sitten kieliopista… ajattelen että sekä suomen että japanin kieliopit ovat sekavat kiinankieliselle (mulle…) koska sanojen loput ovat usein muokkaisi (esim. 食べる=yleiskielen ’syödä’ ja puhekielen ’syö’, 食べます=yleiskielen ’syö’, 食べました=yleiskielen ’söi’, 食べたい=haluta syödä, 食べもの=ruoka/syötävä, jne.). Kiinan kielellä ei ole taas sitä, vaan paljon ’prepositions’, jotka on ehkä myös hankala ymmärtää koska joskus en edes tiedä myöskään miksi niillä tavoilla käytetään näitä sanoja.</p><p>Mutta, kaikki on oma mielipiteeni ja tietysti opetella kiinaa jos sinä haluat tehdä niin!!! Se on niin kaunis kieli ja ei ole mahdoton oppia, vaikka se on erilainen kuin paljon kieliä maailmassa (näkee, suomen kielellä on sama tilanne!). Olen varma että aloitat tykätä sitä kieltä jos yrität ymmärtää sitä :) Japanin kieli on myös tosi mielenkiintoinen ja kannattaa kokeilla.
Suomen kieleni on vielä aika huono, anteeksi. Toivon, että tämä voi auttaa.</p><p>Onnea!</p><h2>In English</h2><p>My mother tongue is Chinese (Mandarin) and I know a little Japanese (I learned it for about 2 years as a child but I still speak it badly). It&#x27;s hard for me to answer your question because there is certainly no easier language in the world for everyone. It&#x27;s a really subjective topic and is strongly based on what your mother tongue is, and then what other languages you can speak.</p><p>UNESCO published a ranking that says Japanese is more difficult than Chinese for English speakers (link here: Language Difficulty Ranking - Effective Language Learning).
But I don&#x27;t think this is necessarily true for a Finnish speaker, because as I&#x27;m learning Finnish these days, I often realise that Japanese is so similar to Finnish. First of all, the word is pronounced in a similar way in Finnish and Japanese, which have long vowels and consonants (e.g. tuuli≠tuli, ちょっと≠ちょと). Chinese does not have it, but there are 4 toons (e.g. 也yě≠叶yè≠爷yé). Therefore you need to make a special &#x27;tone&#x27; for each syllable in Chinese, and if you don&#x27;t yet speak tonal languages, you might find it very difficult...</p><p>Then about grammar... I think both Finnish and Japanese grammars are confusing for a Chinese speaker (me...) because the endings of words are often edited (e.g. 食べる=general language &#x27;eat&#x27; and colloquial &#x27;eat&#x27;, 食べます=general language &#x27;eat&#x27;, 食べました=general language &#x27;ate&#x27;, 食べたい=want to eat, 食べもの=food/eating, etc.). Chinese again doesn&#x27;t have that, but a lot of &#x27;prepositions&#x27;, which may also be difficult to understand because sometimes I don&#x27;t even know why those words are used in those ways either.</p><p>But, all is my opinion and of course learn Chinese if you want to do so!!! It is such a beautiful language and not impossible to learn, although it is different from a lot of languages in the world (you see, Finnish is the same situation!). I&#x27;m sure you&#x27;ll start to like the language if you try to understand it :) Japanese is also really interesting and worth a try.</p><p>My Finnish is still pretty bad, sorry. I hope this can help.</p><p>Good luck!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>